Good evening everyone. Welcome to the
March 23rd finance committee meeting. As
you can see
by the agenda, it is setting up to be a
worldrecord
meeting. So,
let's try and stick to that and we're
going to kick it off with you, Miss
Smiley, with temporary resolution 3826
coming through law committee.
>> All right. I do have a riveting one to
start us off. So, we are asking council
to approve the city settlement and
release of claims with six remnant
defendants as part of a n a multi-dist
litigation known as the national opioid
claim settlement. So previous a previous
council allowed a previous law director
um to enter into this and the city
participated and now we have the
opportunity to recover from those six
defendants who worked out a a potential
agreement. So the too long didn't read
version we would be agreeing to
authorizing the city to join the
settlement group to receive funds from
defendants and the defendants are
actually the opioid distributors. Did I
get that correct? Okay.
>> Okay.
Very well done. Any questions.
>> Well, director Hall, anything to add?
>> Great.
>> Three readings and Stephen will be my
second.
>> Okay. Three readings. Mr. Auger second.
Thank you very much. Temporary
resolution 3926. It's coming through
water pollution. Mr. Als.
>> Yes. Darren's here tonight to discuss
this resolution.
>> Uh, good evening all. On October 13th of
last year, we submitted a request for
legislation to apply for an energy grant
for upgrades to the Southwater treatment
plant. The grant amount was for
$256,000.
Um, we received assistance through
Amoresco to conduct an energy audit to
help secure this funding. Um, earlier
this year, we were notified by the Ohio
Department of Development um that we had
been awarded this energy grant, but the
funds must be utili utilized by January
31st, 2027. Given the project's
timeline, it's crucial that we begin
work as soon as possible. and we would
like to do a design build contract which
would be the fastest way to move
forward. This resolution will allow us
to initiate negotiations with Amoresco
for a design build. Um you'll see
additional legislation coming very soon
to enter into a contract once we
finalize all the details.
Also we uh our share part of this grant
has been allocated in the 2026 budget.
Um, and the funds will be distributed
through our 6027 account, which is our
capital improvement project fund. Do you
have any questions?
Any questions?
Okay, we're going to ask for two
readings and Amy's going to be my
second.
>> Okay,
>> thanks Darren.
>> All right, thank you.
>> Y, thank you.
All right, those are the only two new
resolutions we have and we have one new
ordinance. It's temporary ordinance 726
that's coming through code enforcement
and zoning. Mr. Sully.
>> Yes, sir. This is the final plat for the
victory comments complex. And if our
city planner would just come up and
cover that real quick. I think it's
pretty straightforward.
Hi, good evening. Yes, this is for
Victory Commons. It's up off of Election
House Road. Um so by accepting the plat
this plat you'll be accepting um for the
city of Lancaster the rightway for the
sidewalk and the left turn lane.
Any questions? And this was accepted or
this was approved by the planning
commission on March 12th.
Thank you.
>> No questions. Great.
And then Tom, I have three readings of
Mr. Nisley as your correct
>> second.
>> Okay,
that's it as far as resolutions and
ordinances. We have department updates.
Do we have anyone here for department
updates?
Yes, ma'am.
So, I know several of you have been
included in emails uh over the past
several months about some debris that is
in Feder's Run along the high school
trail from the new high school down to
basically the football fields or the
basketball courts. So, Lancaster High
School has a group of students. It's one
of their um student led clubs that is
going to be doing a cleanup this
Thursday from 3:00 to 5:00 p.m. And the
city of Lancaster is going to be
assisting in that. So, we offered to
have some equipment there to help haul
away some of the heavier items.
Apparently, there's maybe a portallet
that's still in the river from last
year's flooding event, as well as some
other larger items. So, the city's going
to be helping uh get some of those
heavier things. And um again, it's a
studentled volunteer opportunity. I
think that there'll be some teachers and
some club adviserss out there. Um but I
know several of you had expressed
interest. So I thought I would open that
up and again offer that to any of you
who may want to be there as well to help
volunteer on that cleanup.
>> Any questions?
>> Thank you very much, Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes. Uh many of you know that uh Chief
Snyder was away from us for a little
while on a uh
on a pretty prestigious assignment. He
was a member of the 291st session of the
FBI National Academy at Quantico,
Virginia. I'm going to read a little bit
of this because I think it's important
you understand how significant this is
for us. U it's an elite selection
process. Less than 1% of law enforcement
officers worldwide are selected to
attend the academy. It's academically
rigorous in that it is upper level
college courses along with physical
challenges including culminating in a
and chief if you can correct me if I'm
wrong a 6.1
uh or 6.1 mile run
>> yeah uh called the yellow brick road and
the yellow brick road was Larry was
designed by the US Marine Corps
>> of course
>> and a challenge for the FBI national
academy uh if they complete this
successfully and uh it's pretty
challenging physically. Um they receive
a yellow brick with the academy number
stamped on the yellow brick. Uh Chief
Snder, as you would expect, uh graduated
uh and we are very pleased to recognize
that achievement. I think it's uh it's
really something to be proud of and the
city itself can be proud that we have a
graduate of the FBI National Academy.
Sorry, I'm writing down I'm writing
everything down. Um, anyone else for
department updates?
Chief, you don't want to come up and
talk about that or is that for later?
>> You did a great job. Like I said,
>> fair enough.
>> When your legs heal, you can come up to
the podium later. Well, I do have
something update actually.
>> All right.
>> Give me the podium.
>> I spoke it into existence. You're
>> um many of you know we have an officer
that comes in uh for every council
meeting. One of those rotating officers
is Andrew Bennett. Uh Andrew worked with
me on night shift when I was a brand new
sergeant. Um he's worked with me just
about everywhere I've been. He's an
officer in our DARE unit. U very
respected officer. Has been in and out
of our schools. The kids love him. Um
he's just a great guy and uh you'll see
him once about every three weeks here.
He's recently taken the promotional test
and will be and will be promoted to
sergeant. So we will hate to lose him
out of the DARE unit, community services
unit, but uh I couldn't ask for a better
um candidate to be sergeant and he's
going to serve the citizens very very
well. So uh just a public congrats to
Andrew since I'm here. So
>> thank you.
Anyone else for department updates?
>> Seeing none, I'll kick it to President
Porter for tonight's meeting prep.
>> Um, just one item in particular. Uh,
temporary resolution 3426 was
inadvertently left off for second
reading. So, that'll be added back into
everybody's agenda. Um, and it will be a
second uh three readings.
Okay.
Any other items for finance?
>> Seeing none, I'll take a motion. We
adjourn.
>> So moved.
>> Second.
>> We are adjourned at 609.
>> Nine whole minutes.
Uh the regular uh March 23rd city
council meeting will commence at 6:30 at
the published time.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 740-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
Great automotive service is just around
the corner at the Buckeye family of
dealerships. Whether it's Buckeye Nissan
at Hillyard, Georgeesville Nissan at the
Georgeesville Auto Mall, Buckeye Honda
of Lancaster, Buckeye Toyota of
Lancaster, or Buckeye Collision Center
in Hillyard. Team Buckeye services all
makes and models at each location,
utilizing modern practices with hundreds
of years of experience, giving you peace
of mind. That's how we Buckeye
if you're able and join me in a moment
of silence for the additional service
members we've lost in the conflict in
Iran.
I now call the March 23rd,
2026 Lancaster City Council meeting to
order. Please join me in the pledge of
allegiance.
I pledge algiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands. One nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als here.
>> Mr. Bishack
>> here.
>> Mr. Carr
>> Miss Cohen
>> here. Mrs. Who
>> here. Mr. Mr. Nisley
>> here,
>> Mr. Og
>> Mr. Skunover
>> here,
>> Miss Smiley
>> and Mr. Sully
>> here.
>> Let the record reflect that all 10
members of Lancaster City Council are
present this evening. We now move to the
reading and disposing of the journal.
>> I have regular meeting minutes dated
March 9th, 2026.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the journal.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to receive
and file the journal. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
All those same sign. All those opposed
same sign. Reports of city officials.
>> I have six of them this evening. I have
email dated March 9th, 2026 regarding
Hawakin Township annexation public
records request submitted by law
director Stephanie Hall. Email dated
March 10th, 2026 regarding February 2025
collection report submitted by tax
commissioner Amy Hamilton. series of
emails between council member Robert
Nicely, council clerk Scott, and law
director Stephanie Hall dated March
19th, 2026 regarding legislation
requests on feathered flag regulations.
Email dated March 20th, 2026 regarding
temporary resolution 39-26 submitted by
environmental engineer Denise Cruz.
Email dated March 20th, 2026 regarding
final plat for Victory Commons
development of election house road
submitted by city planner Chasen Carter.
Email dated March 23rd, 2026 regarding
annual audit letter to council and city
administration submitted by audit
auditor Nettles.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of city
officials.
>> Second motion and second to receive and
file the reports of city officials. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I. I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Now move
to communications.
>> I do have two this evening. I have email
dated March 13, 2026 regarding public
records requests on a list of arrests in
2025 submitted by Joe Boris and mail
that was received March 20th, 2026
regarding pamplants to all um that were
delivered to all of city hall uh
submitted by
Bohova.
We'll just go with Z Ho U.
>> Uh, Mr. President, I'd like to make a
motion to receive and file the
communications.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to receive
and file the communications. All those
um in favor signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. We have no
special presentation or awards this
evening. And we have no petitions or and
memorials this evening. We've now
reached the time in the council agenda
for permission of voters and taxpayers
to address council. If you would so
choose to address council this evening,
please move to the podium and put your
name and address on the sign-in sheet.
You would have three minutes to address
council this evening.
Good evening, council members and city
administration. My name is Brian
Everett, and I am here this evening to
discuss about uh my least favorite
topic, despite what you may think and
how frequently I speak about it, which
is road safety, street safety,
pedestrian safety. Um, in the time since
last council meeting, there are two
instances in the city that I'm aware of
where vehicles have jumped the curb and
hit things that are off of the street.
One of them being Firehouse Park, uh,
where somebody jumped the curb, hit a
telephone pole. Um, an area where people
play, uh, frequently, especially with
the warmer weather. Um, and St. Mary's
from across the street has their recess.
Uh, additionally, in the last couple
days, there was a uh car that hit and
went into the salon across from
Tibario's. Apologize, I can't think of
the name of it. I don't go to a lot of
salons. Um, but I think that this is
indicative of issues with our street
design. irrespective of any traffic
safety studies or understanding of
traffic engineering or or physics or
anything like that, having two vehicles
jump the curb and hit things that are
off of the street should be enough to
anecdotally realize that we have some
problems with our street design. And I
realize that nobody here on city council
is at fault. Uh nobody here in the city
administration or employee was here.
This has been going on since 1950s. Um,
and I would suggest that now is the
time, if not well past the time, to
begin the same incremental changes that
made our streets more dangerous to make
our streets more safe. Um, we shouldn't
have to rely on the perfect driver being
out there. That person doesn't exist.
There's 40,000 people a year this in
this country that are killed in traffic
crashes. We shouldn't have to rely on
extra safety forces being around to make
somebody stop speeding or not speed. We
should design streets that do not
physically allow you to go fast enough
to jump off of the street and hit a
building. Thank you.
>> Is there anybody else who wishes to
address city council this evening?
>> How you doing?
My name is Terrence Fe.
Um, I'm here to talk about our law
enforcement
on the house on 6th Avenue.
Oh, no, the house on Pierce. Sorry, I
was thinking one on six. Um, first law
enforcement.
They're flying through towns
or every time they get a service call,
they're flying up and down Fifth,
especially on the west side. Got kids
out there.
And I somewhat talked to him already a
little bit about it. Um, going up Main
Street from Walmart, going back to the
station,
doing 45, 50 m an hour, cutting through
downtown,
30, 40 mph backside of that hill. Woo!
They're flying going out Stells Road.
Deal with all that mess out there.
Um, I believe I think that the city
needs to look at it. Look at every
service call, 911 calls.
Um, I get it. the speed limits in town.
I can tell you every speed limit in this
city on the outside of it, even in the
county, every road,
there's no expect, you know, there's no
excuse why law enforcement is going to a
service call without running hot red and
blues on.
OC does not permit them to run above
that speed limit. I followed unit uh 323
the other morning.
flying down Memorial Drive 56.
You know what that is? That's 35. You
know where he was headed?
Police Department.
What was so
wrong at the police department? Why this
officer
booked down Memorial Drive?
Yeah. Makes you wonder. A lot of people
wonders. A lot of people on the west
side wonders. And I get it. There's a
lot of crime on the west side. I get it.
But with these cruisers, it's going to
hit somebody eventually. And all it
takes is somebody on the cruiser to just
look over to that pad, see what the
service call is. Oh, it's next two
blocks up. Pop. Dog walks out. Kid walks
out.
Yesterday, I counted over like 100 dogs.
100 people out walking their dogs.
yesterday. LPD,
they're running from call to call,
flying,
no red and blues on.
I get it that people think 35 is 85.
I get it. 25 is 75. That includes the
residents of this city.
People making a left into the right
lanes.
We should get together. all of you guys,
including the police chief, like
Zanesville did, and come up with a
traffic division, only strictly dealing
with the traffic problems in Lancaster.
And if that officer needs to go on a
domestic call or on whatever other
calls, pull that officer.
>> Sir, you've reached your 3minut limit.
>> Thank you.
>> Is there anybody else who wishes to
address Lancaster City Council this
evening during public comment?
My name is Coard. One thing I wanted to
bring up here,
>> sir, if if you could just step back from
the mic just a bit. You're a little bit
muffled.
>> All right. Uh, one thing I wanted to
bring up, and everyone's probably
experienced this. I'm getting sick and
tired of these car boomers coming up
behind you, beside you, just blasting
your brains out. They're playing this
crap through uh thousands of watts
amplifiers, and no, no one seems to
care. I mean, don't people care about
their little children? Uh military
coming home with PTSD?
Uh super pets with super sensitive
hearing. They can't speak for
themselves. I mean, it's ridiculous. The
the these I call them low life maggots
with a street gang pump punk mentality.
That's what they are to me. And I got
news for you. If I was president and I
had my way, they'd be on the front line.
I' I'd give them something loud to
listen to that they wouldn't forget. and
they wouldn't come back in this country
until they changed because that's that's
a big part of what's wrong with this
country. Too many people feel sorry for
the victimiz the victimizer than they do
the victim. You know, some something
needs to be done done about this. You
know, they're just they're getting by. I
don't know where all these people's
coming from. Everyone knows that they're
building apartments and condos on every
side of town. And I I told people and
other people said this. I think they're
coming from clumps. Well, if you watch
the news out of CL, you know, the local
news, there's a murder about every day.
Multiple murder. Um, hit and runs become
a normal thing. You couldn't pay me to
live in that city. And I question, are
we going to become that way? We had
three I think we had three murders last
year.
So, people better wake up or you're
you're going to lose your rights. You're
not going to have any. What What did all
our military in the past fight for? just
to have their face fit in.
You know, it's ridiculous.
Um,
a couple a couple years ago, I had an
incident happen up on East Main, the
street comes out between Wendy's and the
Dairy Queen. And I got out of my car.
This guy come up behind me and the light
was red. I was going to turn on Main
Street and he was just booming like
everybody else does, other people. And I
got out of my car and I said, "You need
to turn that down." Well, guess what? He
got out of his car and he had a ball
about this size. He said, "I already
used this one. One person." So, what
what's that tell you? And late and I
turned left on Main Street and I was
going to go down to the police station,
which I did. And shortly after I did, he
come in before I filed a report and he
didn't. He lied about everything. He
said, "I walked around his car, stuck my
head in his window, threatened him,
which is all wise.
So that goes to show you what kind of
characters these people are. And you
know, it's just like Ben Franklin once
said, "Evil flourishes when good men do
nothing." So we can't sit around with
their sitting on their thumbs. Like I
said before, there goes your rights out
the window. So I I hope everyone does
some thinking on that. Okay. Thank you.
>> Is there anybody else? this evening that
would like to address city council.
We thank you for attending tonight's
meeting
reports of standing committees.
>> I have two this evening. I have finance
committee meeting agenda dated March
20th, 2026 submitted by Mr. Skoover. I
have code enforcement and zoning meeting
dates dated March 23rd submitted by or
23rd, 2026 submitted by Mr. Sullie.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of
standing committees.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to receive
and file the reports of standing
committees. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. U reports
of special committees.
>> There are no reports.
>> Thank you. We have no public hearing
this evening. We'll now move on to the
reading of resolutions. Beginning with
third reading of temporary resolution
2526.
A resolution to authorize all actions
necessary to accept a Northeast Ohio
Public Energy Council 2026 Energized
Community Grant. This is through finance
committee, Mr. Skoonover and Mr. Als.
>> Council member Spoonover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution 2526.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion, a second to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 2526. Any
discussion?
Uh, no. Just to recap, this is a a noc
grant where the funds are going to be
used to upgrade um some lighting in city
hall.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes. Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skover.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Smiley.
>> And Mr. Sully.
>> Yes.
>> Motion to pass and grow and enter upon
the written record. Temporary resol
resolution 2526 passes 10 to zero.
Temporary resolution 2726.
>> A resolution to increase and decrease
appropriations in the water revenue fund
to cover a shortfall in the retirement
benefits account. It's through water
water pollution control committee. This
is through Mr. Bisjack and Miss Cohen.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record the resolution
temporarily number 27-26.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
2726. Any discussion? Council member
Biz.
>> Uh just a brief recap, Mr. President.
This legislation is seeking to transfer
$5,983.66
from the administration uh salary line
item to the retirement line item in
water. I was just accidentally
appropriated that line item, so we're
just correcting that. That's all. Thank
you, Mr. President.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. OG,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Scoover.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sullie,
>> Motion passing and gross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary resolution
2726 passes 10 to zero. Temporary
resolution 2826.
>> A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to enter into a contract
for the construction of the Frederick
Street sewer separation project. Mr.
Water Pollution Control Committee, Mr.
Bisjack and Miss Coit.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. And I move
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record of the
resolution temporarily number 28-26.
>> A second.
>> Have a motion, a second to pass, gross,
and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 2826. Any
discussion? Council member Bisjack.
>> Uh once again, just a simple recap. This
legislation uh seeks to allow the safety
service director here to enter into a
contract to begin construction on the
Frederick Street uh sewer separation
project, which is a project that's been
mandated by the Ohio Environmental
Protection Agency. That's all I have.
Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. OG,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Scooter,
>> Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> Temporary resolution 2826 passes 10 to
zero. Temporary resolution 3126,
>> a resolution to increase and decrease
appropriations in the general fund 10001
to cover a uniform allowance for a
recent promotion within the Lancaster
Fire Department and to declare an
emergency. This is through safety
committee, Mr. Bisjack and Mr. Al.
>> Council member Bisjack. Uh, thank you,
Mr. President. This uh legislation is
seeking to transfer $4,800 here within
the fire department uh to allow for the
purchase of four new fire uniforms. One
for an assistant fire chief and then
three for new firefighters we have on
staff.
>> Did you make a motion already?
>> Oh, I'm sorry. I I apologize. Got ahead
of myself. I I I move that council pass
and engross upon the written record
temporary resolution number 31-26.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
pass gross enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 3126.
Can we dispense with discussion?
>> Yes, we can. Okay. Thank you.
>> Okay. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. OG,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> Temporate resolution 3126 passes 10 to
zero. We now move on to the second
reading of resolutions beginning with
temporary resolution
3226.
>> A resolution to increase receipts
appropriate from the unencumber balance.
Amend the certificate with the county
auditor in the LDOT improvement fund
3014 to amend the certificate of
appropriations and appropriate from the
unencumbered balance in the general
improvement fund 3016
and the 3M street
improvement levy fund 20009 for funding
of the Arbor Valley Drive Improvement
Fund and to declare an emergency. This
is through public works committee, Mr.
Carr and Miss Smiley.
>> Council member Carr. Mr. President, I
move to that council suspend its rules
and wave the third reading of resolution
temporarily numbered 32-26.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to suspend
the rules and wave the third reading of
temporary resolution 3226.
Any discussion? Council member Carr.
>> Um, no, not at this time.
>> Thank you. Uh, any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes. Miss Cohen,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary resolution
3226 passes 10 to zero. Council member
Carr.
>> Mr. President, I would like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record resolution
temporarily number 32-26.
>> Second. We have a motion and a second to
pass, engross, and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
3226.
Any discussion? Council member Carr.
>> As presented in the last meeting, um
this is to accept the funding from uh
the uh the contribution from the city
schools and appropriate the other funds
for the Arbor Valley Drive improvement
uh um project. And um that's it.
>> Okay. Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the RO. Mr.
Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes. Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Temporary resolution 3226 passes by a
vote of 10 to zero. Temporary resolution
3526.
>> 304.
>> Oh, sorry. 3426.
>> It's the one I missed. Sorry.
>> Yes. Nope. You're all good. a resolution
to authorize the service safety director
to apply for the 2026 AARP community
challenge grant program and to declare
an emergency. This is through finance
committee. Mr. Skoverver and Mr. Sully.
>> Council member Skunover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the third reading of temporary
resolution 3436.
>> Second.
>> 3426.
>> 26.
>> What' I say? 36.
>> I don't want to go that far.
>> Okay.
>> All right.
>> Okay. So, we have a motion and a second
to suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary resolution 3426.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> No. Thanks.
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes. Mr. Nisley,
>> no.
>> Mr. OG,
>> yes.
Mr. Skunover.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary resolution
3426.
Passes by a vote of 9 to1. Council
member Skoonover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution 3426.
>> Second.
>> A motion second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 3426. Any discussion?
>> Just to recap, this is allows the
service safety director to submit an
ARPA grant for um some handicap ramps uh
owned by the city to be used by city
businesses if need be.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
>> Yes, Mr. President.
>> Council member Nicely.
>> Yep. I just want to say um a thank you
to law director Hall and service safety
director Woody for um working with me on
this legislation. We had we had some
discussions about um some issues that I
that I foraw with liability
and uh so I just want to say I just
wanted to say thank you for them for
working on it with me. We did try to
come to a uh to some sort of a
alternative scenario for this
legislation. Unfortunately um the way
that it was written and the way that the
grant is the grant is structured we
couldn't quite get there. Um I still do
and I appreciate the goal of the
legislation. And I do think that there
needs to be more handicap access um with
our businesses,
but I still do have concerns with the
ramps being stored, maintained, and ma
and managed by the city for use by
private businesses. I still maintain
that uh the private businesses in
question if they have concerns about
folks being able to access their
business should be the ones responsible
for owning m and maintaining those ramps
themselves. Um and uh so I just and I I
do think that while the city does have
some liability protections in law, um I
nothing stops someone from bringing suit
against the city anyway if there if
there were any injuries that occurred
from these ramps that'll be owned by the
city. And so for those reasons, I still
um cannot support this resolution, but I
appreciate the intent. Thank you, Mr.
President.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Cohen.
>> Mrs. Hoop.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Nisley.
>> No.
>> Mr. OG.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Skunover.
>> Mr. Miss Smiley.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Sully.
>> Temporary resolution 3426 passes by a
vote of 9 to1. Temporary resolution
3526. A resolution to authorize the
service safety director to readvertise
for bids and enter into a contract for
the construction of the East 6th Avenue
bridge over Feder's Run replacement
project and to hire a consultant to
provide construction inspection services
and to declare an emergency. This is
through public works committee Mr. Carr
and Mr. Vijger.
>> Council member Carr.
>> Second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 3526.
We'll now move on to the first reading
of resolutions, beginning with temporary
resolution 3826,
>> a resolution authorizing the mayor to
act on behalf of the city of Lancaster
and enter into any and all agreements or
settlements necessary to participate in
the new national opioid settlements with
associated
incorporated and American Associated
Pharmacies. JN Smith Corporation,
Louisiana Wholesale Drug Company, Inc.
Morris and Dixon Co. Company, North
Carolina Mutual Wholesale Drug Company
Incorporated, and United Natural Food,
excuse me, Foods Incorporated, including
its subsidiaries,
Super Value and Advantage Logistics, and
to declare an emergency. This is through
law committee, Miss Smiley and Mr. OG.
>> Council member Smiley,
>> first of three readings. First of three
readings on temporary resolution 3826.
Temporary resolution 3926.
>> A resolution to authorize the surface
service safety director to wave the
request for qualifications and negotiate
a design build contract for a energy
upgrade grant for the southwater
treatment plant and rehabilitations and
to declare an emergency. It's through
water water pollution control committee.
Mr. Als and Miss Cohen. Council member a
>> first of two readings.
>> First of two readings on temporary
resolution 3926.
That concludes the reading of
resolutions for this evening's meeting.
We now move on to the reading of
ordinances beginning with a temporary
ordinance 4-26.
an ordinance authorizing the mayor to
grant four permanent supplemental
easements to the Ohio Power Company
necessary for the construction and
maintenance of electric facilities and
to declare an emergency. This through
law committee, Miss Smiley and Mr. Carr.
>> Council member Smiley.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I would like
to make a motion that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
ordinance temporarily numbered 4-26.
>> Second. We have a motion, a second to
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary ordinance 4-26.
Any discussion? Council member Smiley.
>> Just a reminder, this is um a has been
working in the city for the last two
years on transmission updates and they
are requesting four additional
supplemental easements to complete the
work. So, our rightaway manager and the
city of engineer or the city engineer
have reviewed and approved the request
and it's important to know that they've
approved the proposed rate calculated on
the value of the land which was deemed
appropriate. The work is on the south
side of Lancaster along Logan Lancaster
Road and then um US 33 and Hornsville
Road.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Pisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> yes. Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. OG,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> Temporary ordinance 4-26 passes 10 to
zero. We now move on to second reading
uh with temporary ordinance 5-26.
>> An ordinance to amend permanent
ordinance 63-25,
the management pay ordinance to add an
assistant prosecutor position for a
limited period of time and to declare an
emergency. Mr. Finance Committee. Mr.
Skunover or Mr. Sully.
>> Council member Skunover.
>> Be the second of three readings, please.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
ordinance 5-26. Temporary ordinance
6-26.
>> An ordinance authorizing the service
safety director to execute a lease
amendment with Park National Bank and to
declare an emergency. This is through
law committee. Mr. Carr and Mr. O.
>> Council member Carr.
>> Second of three readings. Second of
three readings on temporary ordinance
6-26.
Uh we now move on to first reading be of
ordinances beginning with temporary
ordinance 7-26.
>> An ordinance to accept the final plat
for the Victory Commons development.
This through code enforcement in zoning
committee. Mr. Sully and Mr. Nisley.
>> Council member Sley.
>> Thank you. First of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
ordinance 7-26.
That be that brings us to the end of the
reading of ordinances this evening. We
have no tabled legislation.
Do we have any unfinished business? We
have no unfinished business this
evening. We'll now move on to new
business. I believe we have a liquor
permit matter.
Miss Stephanie Hall, would you like to
This is the same license that we went
through a little we touched base on it a
little bit last meeting and we wanted to
look into more of it. Yes, thank you.
So, um the council members all received
the information that LPD put together.
Um, and while there are only a total of
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven
calls um, at 1454 North Columbus Street
where the Aendale um, drive-thru is
located. Um, several of those are rather
concerning. Um, one of those um, the
clerks themselves called in because of
12-year-old stole THC vapes. Um, another
parent called in because her 14-year-old
daughter came home with weed and a THC
vape. Um, and then a another citizen
called in because his minor son was sold
marijuana at that business. Um, the one
other call on there that that probably
caught everybody's attention was the
major crimes unit assistance and
investigation. Um, and that included the
major crimes unit going in and seizing
hundreds of items that contained THC
illegally. Um, so you know, they're
selling THC illegally. We know that
much. Um, the Ohio Investigative Unit
has also investigated and prosecuted uh
clerks there for selling underage
alcohol to minors as well. So, they're
illegally selling THC products. They are
illegally selling alcohol. I believe the
one um the one car that had two
teenagers in it was a 17year-old and a
15year-old. Um, I don't know how anybody
could, you know, think that a 15y old
would possibly be a 21 year old, but
regardless, um, we had one of those in
24 and one of those in 25. The one in 24
we convicted. Um, the clerk had no
social security number and, uh, only
provided a first name. So, it's really
hard to track an individual who
continues to do things that they're not
supposed to do, um, with that kind of
information. The second individual again
had no social security number. Um and he
failed to appear to court. So, you know,
we can't issue a warrant. We can't do
anything about it because we don't have
social security numbers to keep track of
these people. Um in addition, I reached
out. So, Scott Duff, the uh commander of
the major crimes unit, told me that he
thought it would be a good idea to reach
out to Lancaster High School because he
knew they they had also had some issues
there. Um and I did. I reached out and
spoke with principal Burray who advised
that multiple students at Lancaster High
School have been caught in possession of
electronic smoking devices and admitted
to Lancaster High School administration
that they're buying the devices at this
location. The ease and accessibility of
this these devices to minors is a health
and safety concern for parents,
students, and the community of
Lancaster. Uh so for those reasons, I
would ask that you all vote to object to
the transfer this evening so that we can
have an opportunity to speak with the
Division of Liquor Control about the
ongoing issues at this address and
maybe, you know, do something to address
those for public safety. Thank you.
>> That was a good question.
>> Yeah, just a second. Um, council member
OG.
>> So, they're applying for a liquor
license, not a THC.
>> No, they have a liquor license and the
liquor license is being transferred from
one entity to another entity.
>> Typically, these are
>> Are they changing ownership?
>> Not necessarily. No, that that that's
what I was going to say. Typically, it's
a change in in name of the permit holder
only.
But so far,
unless I misheard, they had one
violation of selling to underage.
>> They've had multiple violations of
selling to underage for alcohol. They
they can't sell marijuana. That is
illegal. Yeah.
>> But there was a big focus towards
selling THC and marijuana,
>> but this is for liquor.
>> Correct. But liquor liquor
establishments are not supposed to sell
anything illegally, right? the Division
of Commerce um is supposed to monitor
that and control that and they did by
sending in Ohio investigative unit
officers, but the maximum that they will
do is charge the clerk who sells
underage. And like I said, we're having
trouble, you know, getting those people
to even come to court because they don't
have social security numbers. So, I
can't really enforce the law against
them.
>> That's all we got.
>> Thank you, Council Member S. What's the
window of time we have to take either
accept or I know there's a a a time
frame that we have to respond.
>> Yeah, we're already um we have like
maybe a few more days to get through.
>> It just has to be postmarked by a
certain date and I believe it's two to
three days out from now. But
>> so if we say no or object
>> what do does that clock start over
again? Do they have a chance to
>> address the concerns or
>> not here, but they will. The Division of
Liquor Control will set a hearing um so
that I can address the the issues that
we have with whoever the attorney is for
the seller and the buyer
>> or the transfer and the the transfer of
the permit.
>> And then would you come would it come
back to us after that or is this out of
our hands at that point?
>> At that point, it's out of your hands.
It goes to the Division of Liquor
Control
>> and then they have the say of your name.
Okay.
>> Yep.
>> Thank you.
>> So if we vote no, we're we're putting
these people out of business.
>> No, you're just objecting to the
transfer of the license. There will be a
hearing like I said, so they get due
process. You know, it goes through the
Division of Liquor Control. That's not a
local um that's not a local process.
>> So this is our only chance to address
this. if we say I mean it sounds like
the people that are running this are
fairly irresponsible
it sounds like and it makes me want to
vote no but I also know that the liquor
licenses are valuable and if you if we
say no then they've lost a business
they've lost their business
>> so I will say this it's not your only
chance to address it but it is your best
chance to address it because when they
need something from you is the time to
make sure that they are responsible
business owners in the city of
Lancaster. Um, you know, public safety
is obviously a concern for everybody
around this table and I think that now
is the time to address it because we're
aware of the issues. Number one, they've
been brought to our attention. Um, and
two, we have the ability to address
those. In the past, we have objected pre
previously and then taken the the time
between, you know, the objection and the
hearing date to work out some kind of,
you know, system for ensuring that we're
going to be able to hold people
responsible for their illegal actions.
Um, and making it easier for law
enforcement to go in and do inspections
and make sure that that nothing um, you
know, nothing that's not on the books is
not happening.
Law Director Hall, if I might.
>> Um, with with a particular circumstance
like this, when there's a transfer, you
have an opportunity as a municipality to
object. Is that correct?
>> Yes, sir. That's what you're
>> And then when that liquor permit is up
for renewal again, which is, I believe,
yearly. Is that correct?
>> We would also have an opportunity at
that time as well.
>> I don't think it's yearly. No, not um
not
>> It's not yearly.
>> I apologize. I don't believe it is. No.
Um because 1454 North Columbus Street
has not come in front of you, I know,
for at least several years. Um and I
don't know if that's because there were
transfers previously or what was
happening, but no, you don't have an
opportunity to do anything annually
about it.
>> Okay. I ju I just know that other
municipalities typically and I know that
other local jurisdictions do get
opportunities to object to renewals. so
that um they have that opportunity as
well. So anyway,
>> the clerk of council receives all of
those. So if she's got one, I I don't
know about it. I'm sorry.
>> Okay.
>> Council member Nicely.
>> Law Director Hall, um what are some
other are there some other tools that
this council could take um in addition
to objecting to this liquor permit if if
let's say if hypothetically if the
council wish to take further action
against this particular establishment?
Yeah, there's not really anything good
because the problem is for the for the
illegal sales, all we can do is charge
the individual who is selling the
underage alcohol. Um, we can't charge
the business owner. And because these
are misdemeanor sales, it's not a
nuisance facility. Um, so we can't do
anything take any kind of nuisance
abatement action against them. Um, so I
will say LPD and Major Crimes had looked
at them, and I'm not trying to throw
anybody under the bus here, but they had
looked at the quality of life issues
that are being raised by the sale of,
um, you know, black market marijuana to
children. Um, and the problem is all of
those items that are seized, the, you
know, the THC, the packaging is
obviously, you know, you can't rely on
it. So, they have to send it all off to
be tested and they have to determine the
quantity in each individual item. Um,
and that goes to the Ohio Attorney
General's office, which you know,
obviously their lab is doing some other
very important things with, you know,
fentanyl and carfentinol and meth and
all of the other drugs that they have to
deal with. And so, this kind of goes to
the bottom of the list. Um, and you
know, there's not a whole lot that that
can be done.
>> Thank you.
>> Yep.
Okay. I have a motion if there I have a
motion. If there are no other questions,
Mr. President,
>> take the motion.
>> All right. Mr. uh Mr. President, I move
that council reject the permit.
>> Okay. That's probably not the proper
form. No.
>> Um we would at this point entertain a
motion to object to the transfer of the
um proposed liquor permit.
>> Then let me rephrase that. Mr.
President, I move then that we object to
the transfer of the permit. Do we have a
second?
>> Second.
>> We have a motion in a second to object
to the transfer of liquor license permit
number 10 09896-1.
>> Please.
>> Yeah, just call the RO.
>> Okay. Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes. Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. OG,
>> yes. Mr. Skunover.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Sully,
>> Okay. Motion carries 10 to zero.
>> Um, in new business tonight, do we can
do committee updates? Does anybody have
committee updates? Who wants to start?
>> I'll start.
>> Okay. Council member Bisjack.
>> Don't have much to share from the safety
committee other than once again, we're
meeting on April 3rd, next Friday, at 8
a.m. in the 1897 conference room. So,
look forward to seeing you all there.
Bright, smiley faces. Okay. Thank you,
Council Member Sal.
>> We for zoning and code enforcement,
we're meeting uh April 9th and there's
going to be a variety of topics uh
that were going to be discussed. So, u
one of which I can we're going to have
more new business after this or because
one of the items was the feather signs
and I think Rob Councilman Eisley wants
to address that.
>> Okay. Get through committee updates.
>> Okay. That's all for now. Council member
Cohen.
>> Um, no update. Administrative services
will meet in May.
>> Thank you. Council member Als,
>> the water water pollution control
committee will meet April 10th at 7:30
a.m.
>> Thank you, Council Member Smiley.
>> Law Committee is planning to meet April
17th at 12:30 in the conference room in
city hall.
>> Great. Council member Og.
>> Nothing to report.
>> Thank you. Council member Spoonover.
Uh, I have nothing to report because you
all get to join me every two weeks right
here.
>> There we go. Same bat time. Same bad.
>> All right, Council Member Carr.
>> Next public works committee meeting will
be April 17th, 1897 conference room at
7:30 a.m.
>> Thank you, Council Member Nisley.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. The service
committee will meet again on May 14th in
the conference room in city hall at 7:30
a.m. Um, and just to just to bring the
committee up to speed or the council up
to speed, um, I anticipate some
legislation in the near future to
address um a uh a wrecked uh sanitation
vehicle um that they have approached me
about that we may need legislation to
purchase a new sanitation vehicle. So uh
that legislation and more details will
be forthcoming, but that's just to kind
of lay it all out there for everybody.
Thank you. Thank you, Council Member
Hoop.
>> Yes, thank you. Um, economic development
is not really busy right now, but we
have our next meeting on April 30th at
7:30 in the morning.
>> Thank you.
Any further new business at this time?
And repres u recognize council member uh
nicely.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. Um, I
know uh, Council Member Sie uh, kind of
alluded to this, but I wanted to bring
to the to this council's attention some
some issues that I that have been raised
to me by some members of the community
when it when it comes in in regards to
the um,
ordinances on uh, pro prohibited signs.
Um, there have been some folks that have
approached me about wanting to be able
to utilize um, they so-called feathered
flags, sometimes called feathered signs.
um and uh and to try to do that in a
responsible way. And so I am uh looking
to address that uh with future
legislation and I'll be working with uh
Chairman Sie and code enforcement and
zoning on that. And so I just wanted to
let everyone know that um this is
something that may that may come up in
the future and uh looking forward to
having more discussions on that and how
to how to uh remove the prohibition on
that which is current uh ordinance uh
and try to try to potentially um open
this up to allow folks to be able to do
that in a responsible way. So thank you.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion on
that particular topic?
Hearing none, any further new business?
Seeing none, we now move to the
announcements of scheduled meetings.
>> I have next regular sessions of council.
April 6, 2026 at 6:30 p.m. here in
council chambers. And then two weeks
later, April 20th, 2026 at 6:30 p.m.
here in council chambers.
>> We have no special meeting scheduled. We
move to regularly scheduled committee
meetings.
>> I have um safety committee April 3rd,
2026 at 8:00 a.m. in the 1897 conference
rooms at city hall. Water water
pollution control committee April 10th
at 2026 at 7:30 a.m. 1897 conference
room in city hall. Law committee meeting
April April 17, 2026 at 12:30 p.m. 1897
conference room in city hall. economic
development meeting April 30th, 2026 at
7:30 a.m. in the 1897 conference room
and then code enforcement and zoning
committee April 9th um 7:30 p.m. or AM,
sorry, in the 1897 conference room.
>> No bills.
>> No bills this evening. Okay, there we
go. No need for an executive session.
I'll now entertain a motion to adjurnn.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make the
motion we adjourn.
>> Second.
>> A motion and second to adjurnn. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. 7:16
p.m. Uh, please uh remember to sign your
legislation before you leave this
evening. Thank you.